最后，形状。
Lastly, shapes.
有人能说出形状吗？
Can anybody name the shape?
只是在开玩笑。
Just kidding.
&gt;&gt; [笑] &gt;&gt; [笑] 我用这个来代表
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] &gt;&gt; [LAUGH] I'm using this to represent
一堆不同的效果类型。
a bunch of different effect types.
所以你有你的异步和错误处理，以及你的事件流，
So you have your async and your error handling, and your event streams,
我们倾向于用类似函子的类型来对它们进行建模。
and we tend to model these with types like the functors.
所以你有你的任务和你的任一个，还有你的这个或那个。
So you have your task and your either, and your this or that.
归根结底，这些东西不会组合，monads 不会组合。
And at the end of the day, these things don't compose, monads don't compose.
所以会发生什么，函子组合，单声道组合，我们会看到这一点。
And so what happens is, functors compose, mono is compose, and we'll see that.
但是如果你必须在你的应用程序中使用 monad，
But if you have to use a monad in your application,
通常情况下，这些东西实际上并不构成。
which is typically the case, these things don't actually compose.
所以，我们专注于标准化形状，
So, we focus on normalizing the shape,
有点像把它们捣碎成一个东西，比如一个 gobstopper 的内部。
kind of mashing them into the one thing like the inside of a gobstopper.
&gt;&gt; [笑] &gt;&gt; 然后你可以把它们结合起来，
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] &gt;&gt; And then you can combine them,
一切都很开心，对吧？
and it's all happy, right?
所以标准化效果类型
So normalizing the effect types
整个应用程序是您可能想要做的事情。
throughout the app is something that you probably want to do.
我不认为它总是必要的，但必须是必要的。
I don't think it's necessarily necessary all the time but, necessarily necessary.
拥有标准化的效果形状只是一个很好的指导原则，所以
It's just good guiding principle to have a normalized shape of your effects so
你最终可能会制作一个应用程序 monad，一切都落入其中。
you end up making maybe an app monad, and everything falls into that.
所以一切都很好。
And so everything kind of composes.
我们将看到不同的策略，
And there's different strategies as we'll see,
我们会看到自由的单子，自由的幺半群，那些东西。
we'll see free monads, free monoids, that stuff.